Guide to the Peyton Randolph Gilbert Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Peyton Randolph Gilbert family papers
1760-1905
MS 699
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(3 boxes)
Peyton R. Gilbert is the central figure in these family papers which begin with his father Samuel Gilbert, a judge in Tolland County, Connecticut. The family was based in Gilead and Hebron, Connecticut. The largest part of the papers contains legal and financial papers from the law practices of both Peyton R. and Samuel Gilbert. Also included is family correspondence, with a number of Civil War letters from David J. Gilbert as well as letters from members of the family in the West. Also in the papers are the diaries (1878-1884) of Ralph P. Gilbert and the papers of the Gilead Ecclesiastical Society, including letters from Albert W. and Nellie P. Clark who were living as missionaries in Bohemia in 1872.
Gilbert, Peyton Randolph, 1808-1874
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by purchase, 1944-1953.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This small collection contains papers of the Peyton Randolph Gilbert family and of the towns of Gilead and Hebron, Connecticut. Family members include Peyton R. Gilbert's father, Samuel Gilbert (1734-1818), and mother, Deborah Gilbert, his brothers John H. Gilbert and Charles C. Gilbert, his wife, Anna Porter, and his son Edwin Randolph Gilbert (1808-1874). Also represented in the collection are Ralph P. Gilbert, Ralph D. Gilbert, Sylvester Gilbert, and others whose precise connection to Peyton R. Gilbert is unclear.
A number of the Gilberts were involved in legal and political affairs. Samuel Gilbert was chief justice of the Court of Common Pleas for Tolland County, Connecticut, for 21 years. Sylvester Gilbert was a lawyer and justice of the peace, as was Peyton R. Gilbert, while Ralph P. Gilbert, a farmer by trade, was a member of the Connecticut State Legislature in the years 1880 and 1883. As a result, although fragments of family and business correspondence of Edwin R., Ralph P., Ralph D., and Peyton R. Gilbert are in the collection along with the diaries of Ralph P. Gilbert for the years 1878-1884, the majority of the papers are of a financial and legal nature. Included are papers from the legal practices of Samuel and Peyton R. Gilbert, legal papers relating to the Gilbert family (folders 33, 38), and a collection of legal documents of Peyton R. and Ralph Gilbert and other justices of the peace of Tolland County (folders 41-44). The financial papers in the collection are largely concerned with the estates of Samuel and Peyton R. Gilbert (folders 3, 21-22), although there are also lists of taxable property of residents of Hebron (folder 40) and other miscellaneous financial papers (folders 26-32).
Other materials in the collection include papers of the Gilead School Society and of the Gilead Ecclesiastical Society, among the more interesting of which are letters from Albert W. and Nellie P. Clark, missionaries in Bohemia in 1872. There is also a small amount of correspondence belonging to Mary Hutchinson of Gilead, several sermons possibly written by Edwin R. Gilbert, an unidentified copy book, and various other miscellaneous items.
Biographical / Historical
EDWIN RANDOLPH GILBERT, 1808-1874
EDWIN RANDOLPH GILBERT, son of Hon. Peyton R. and Anna (Porter) Gilbert, was born in Gilead, a parish of Hebron, Conn., Feb. 10, 1808. He entered the Yale Divinity School in 1829 and completed the course in 1832. On the 3d of Oct., 1832, he was ordained over the Congregational Church in Wallingford, Conn., and retired as pastor emeritus, Jan. 1, 1874. His long pastorate was marked by great fidelity and judiciousness. He died of pneumonia at his residence in Wallingford, April 17, 1874, after an illness of eight days. The sermon preached at his funeral by the Rev. Dr. Leonard Bacon, who also preached the sermon at his ordination, is to be published. From August, 1849, until his death, Mr. Gilbert was a member of the Corporation of Yale College.
He was married, May 7, 1833, to Ann S. Langdon, of Hartford, Conn., by whom he had four children. She died Feb. 13, 1841. His second marriage was with Dorcas S., daughter of Rev. Aaron Dutton. (Y. C. 1803) of Guilford, July 26, 1842. She died July 10, 1849, having had three children. He married again, Sept. 7, 1852, Clara, daughter of William Baldwin, of New Haven, who died Aug. 19, 1864. He was again married, Oct. 16, 1865, to Henrietta M. Carrington, of Wallingford; who survives him. Two sons, one by his first and one by his second marriage, are also living, the younger of whom is a graduate of this college.
From Yale University Obituary Record.
Education; Families; Law; Bohemia (Czech Republic) -- Religion; Connecticut; Hebron (Conn.); West (U.S.); Account books; Diaries; Sermons; Clergy; Lawyers; Missionaries; Clark, Albert Warren, 1842-1921; Gilbert, D. J. (David J.); Gilbert, Edwin Randolph, 1808-1874; Gilbert, Ralph P.; Gilbert, Samuel, 1734-1818; Gilbert family
- Inventory, 1760-1905
  - Gilbert, Edwin R.
    - Letter to his parents, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Edwin D. Potter, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gilbert, Peyton R.
    - Incoming letters, 1818-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lists of his taxable property, 1806-1857 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Legal practice
      - Adams, Cynthia: estate papers, 1820-1835 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Bliss family: financial and legal papers, 1779-1884 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
      - Bolles, Edwin C.: promissory notes and accounts payable, 1850-1863 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Gilbert family: papers re the "family fund" established in the will of Samuel Gilbert, 1800-1820 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Johnson, Joel: estate papers, 1847-1853 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Mack family: financial and legal papers, 1798-1853 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
      - Norton, Jethro: estate papers, 1831-1843 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Porter, Hannah: estate papers, 1836-1838 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Porter, Pelatiah: estate papers, 1800, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gilbert, Ralph D. (Y. 1904, Ph.D.): letters to his family, 1901, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gilbert, Ralph P.
    - Incoming letters, 1848, 1862-1874 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Diaries, 1878-1884 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - Railroad passes, 1880, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Gilbert, Samuel
    - Account book, 1760-1797 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Legal and financial papers, 1795-1818 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Estate papers, 1818-1820 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Gilead Ecclesiastical Society
    - Lists of members and miscellaneous financial papers, 1750, 1783, 1797-1883 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Letters to the Sunday School from Albert W. Clark and Nellie P. Clark, missionaries in Bohemia, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Gilead School Society: minutes and legal and financial papers, 1814-1881 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Hutchinson, Mary L.: letters and miscellaneous papers, 1833-1841 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Receipts and other financial papers, 1786-1883, 1890, undated (Box 2, Folder 26-32)
  - Deeds, 1816-1860 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Sermons, 1773-1860 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Copy book, Undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous letters, 1800-1905, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous legal papers, 1820-1889, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous papers, Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Instructions for polishing a stove, Undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Lists of taxable protperty of various residents of Hebron, Connecticut, 1832 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Summons, attachments, complaints, and other legal papers of Peyton R. Gilbert, Ralph Gilbert, and other justices of the peace of Tolland County, Connecticut, 1814-1854, undated (Box 3, Folder 41-44)